Chelsie S. Johnston

Belleville, IL, USA | (312) 402-8294 | chelsiesjohnston@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/chelsiesjohnston | https://chelsie.dev

SUMMARY

Seasoned "started-in-childhood" developer returning to the field with over a decade of professional experience crafting reliable and visually polished web solutions at scale; passionate autodidact with an eagerness to integrate leadership into an already deep front end engineering skill set, as well as expand skills lower down the stack; body of work spans a diverse range of nonprofits, universities, international brands, and government agencies; effective in stakeholder negotiation and requirements gathering; highly communicative remote collaborator with an enthusiasm for process iteration and team development.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Front End Developer, Last Call Media

Remote — Feb 2019 - Aug 2022

Bridged the gap between design and engineering in a fully distributed agency. Acted as a liaison to the design team in an advisory role alongside coding robust, performant experiences and contributing PR reviews as a developer.

Notable projects:

- **New England Foundation for the Arts** Built a decoupled React front end to consume a Drupal-based API for the Creativeground.org website, supporting over 11,000 artists and patrons in fostering creative partnerships
- Mass.gov Paid Family and Medical Leave Supported release testing, uptime monitoring, and reliability for a critical government social program using automated End to End (E2E) testing via Jest and Cypress
- **Blackboard.com** Crafted a WCAG 2.1 compliant component library and theme for the education brand using SCSS and JavaScript, leading to a lower homepage bounce rate and an increase in free trial signups
- Instant Brands (formerly Corelle Brands) Enhanced Instant Brands' Drupal site's styling using SCSS and JS to accommodate on-the-fly addition of new brands, ensuring a cohesive user experience during a pivotal sales period
- Key technologies: JavaScript ES6, TypeScript, React, CSS-in-JS, Twig, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS, PHP, Jest, Cypress, BackstopJS, Git, Docker, CircleCI

Software Engineer II, American Medical Association

Chicago, IL — Aug 2016 - Jul 2018

Built and maintained public and member-facing websites with up-to-the-minute resources for doctors and medical professionals. Collaborated closely with UX designers and contributed code and PR reviews as part of a cross-functional project team.

Notable projects:

- Front End/Style Guide Project leadership Led a front-end team in conceptualizing, developing, and maintaining an integrated component library, providing cohesive, attractive branding across the AMA's diverse web properties; initialized clean front end code standards with a focus on accessibility for end users
- Key technologies: JavaScript ES6, PatternLab, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS, PHP, BackstopJS, Vagrant, Travis, Git

Front End Developer, The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL — May 2013 - Aug 2016 (Front End Developer, UChicago Web Services dept.)

Chicago, IL — Sep 2012 - May 2013 (Project Delivery Contractor, UChicago Project Management Office)

Dual focus as a designer; reshaped departmental processes while supporting the University's outreach and recruitment mission through delivery of websites for degree programs and academic research organizations. Forged empathetic relationships with stakeholders via educational hands-on design sessions, streamlining time to delivery.

Notable projects:

- Client-facing Process Innovation Spearheaded the overhaul of the University's in-house web design process by implementing atomic design principles and transitioning from waterfall to agile project management methodologies, resulting in cost savings and stronger client relationships
- **UChicago News** Designed and developed the UChicago News website using SCSS, JS, and PHP, empowering editors with captivating storytelling capabilities while maintaining a structured content architecture
- **UChicago Sites** Maintained a Drupal template site service that provided over 1,000 University organizations with design and content flexibility while ensuring alignment with the University brand
- Key technologies: JavaScript, jQuery, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS, PHP, BackstopJS, Git

IT Assistant, Spurlock Museum, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL — Sep 2009 - Aug 2011

Notable projects:

- **Web and kiosk development** Conceptualized and built digital experiences for web and in-person exhibit kiosks using HTML, CSS, Javascript, and Adobe Creative Suite, allowing museum patrons to deeply engage with historical artifacts from across the world
- **Accessibility compliance** Tested and documented the patron-facing website's compliance with emerging web accessibility (A11y) standards, making the Museum's collections and events more inclusive

LEADERSHIP AND SPEAKING

Volunteer Technical Lead, Women Who Code - St. Louis, MO

St. Louis, MO - Nov 2023 - present

 Organize and host online and in-person networking events, empowering a diverse population of underserved technical professionals to find community, seek employment, and improve technical skills; provide mentorship for junior developers

Presenter: WWC Coffee Talks 2024 (upcoming); NERD Summit 2020; Midwest Area Drupal Camp 2016

EDUCATION

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Champaign, IL - May 2012

BA Communication, concentration in Sociocultural and Linguistic Anthropology

CONTINUING EDUCATION AND SUPPLEMENTAL SKILLS

- Currently learning Java
- Highly experienced in exploring ambiguous product ideas and architecting them into clearly scoped, organized requirements that meet business goals; adept at engaging with stakeholders to identify potential risks and justify trade-offs
- Committed to supporting Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in tech
- Conscientious and detail oriented; adaptable and at ease in a high pressure environment